<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI version="4.9.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="it">Ragione d’alcune cose segnate nella Canzone d’Annibal Caro</title>
        <title type="sub" xml:lang="it">Venite a’ l’ombra de’ gran gigli d’oro</title>
        <title type="main" xml:lang="en">Reason for some things marked in Annibal Caro’s *Canzone*</title>
        <title type="sub" xml:lang="en"><foreign>Venite a’ l’ombra de’ gran gigli d’oro</foreign></title>
        <author ref="#castelvetro">Lodovico Castelvetro</author>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Author</resp>
          <persName ref="#castelvetro">Lodovico Castelvetro</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Encoding</resp>
          <persName xml:id="FM">Francesca Massarenti</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Translation</resp>
          <persName ref="#FM">Francesca Massarenti</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher ref="#FM">Francesca Massarenti</publisher>
        <date when="2025">2025</date>
        <availability>
          <licence target=" https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This is an open access work licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license.</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <msDesc facs="http://data.onb.ac.at/ABO/%2BZ182114201">
          <msIdentifier>
            <institution>Austrian National Library</institution>
            <idno>*35.Q.171</idno>
          </msIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <msItem>
              <bibl>
                <title type="main">Ragione d’alcune cose segnate nella Canzone d’Annibal Caro</title>
                <title type="sub">Venite a l’ombra de gran gigli d’oro</title>
                <author ref="#castelvetro">Lodovico Castelvetro</author>
                <publisher>Cornelio Gadlandini</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Modena</pubPlace>
                <date when="1559">1559</date>
              </bibl>
            </msItem>
          </msContents>
          <citedRange><locus from="6r" to="9r">ff. 6r–9r</locus></citedRange>
          <citedRange><locus from="10v" to="11v">ff. 10v–11v</locus></citedRange>
          <citedRange><locus from="20v" to="21v">ff. 20v–21v</locus></citedRange>
          <citedRange><locus from="23r" to="24r">ff. 23r–24r</locus></citedRange>
        </msDesc>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>The encoding focuses on the argumentative structure of the work, reconstructing arguments from statements classified as premises, conclusions or inference rules.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>This edition includes only selected parts of the text, based on their relevance to argument analysis.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Punctuation and apostrophes have been modernized to aid comprehension. All abbreviations have been expanded. The consonant clusters -ti- and -tti- followed by a vowel have been replaced with z; etymological hs have been removed. Divergences from modern usage in single and double consonants have been preserved.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="statement">
          <desc>Roles that statements may fill in an argument.</desc>
          <category xml:id="premise">
            <catDesc>Premise</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="rule">
            <catDesc>InferenceRule</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="conclusion">
            <catDesc>Conclusion</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="topic">
          <desc>The topics that are the subject of an argument.</desc>
          <category xml:id="disputed-words">
            <catDesc>Disputed word</catDesc>
            <catDesc>Locution featured in Annibal Caro’s canzone whose permissibility in the context of Petrarchist poetry is questioned by Lodovico Castelvetro.</catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="latinisms">
            <catDesc>Latinisms</catDesc>
            <catDesc>Lexical Latinisms are loanwords from written Latin that are artificially introduced into Italian through phonetic and morphological adaptation, as opposed to hereditary words, which result naturally from uninterrupted phonetic evolution. Latinisms are often employed in poetic texts to elevate the stylistic register.</catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
        <particDesc>
          <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="caro" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/51714622">
              <persName>Annibal Caro</persName>
              <persona xml:id="predella">
                <persName>Predella</persName>
                <note>Fictional author: the text is presented as if written by the janitor of Accademia di Banchi di Roma.</note>
              </persona>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="castelvetro" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/22166452">
              <persName>Lodovico Castelvetro</persName>
              <persona xml:id="anon">
                <persName>Anonymous</persName>
                <note>The text is presented as if written by an anonymous figure.</note>
              </persona>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="petrarca" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/39382430">
              <persName>Francesco Petrarca</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="boccaccio" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/64002165">
              <persName>Giovanni Boccaccio</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="poliziano" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/9867884">
              <persName>Angelo Poliziano</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="lorenzo-medici" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/54169908">
              <persName>Lorenzo de’ Medici</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bembo" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/54144140">
              <persName>Pietro Bembo</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="quintilian" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/34451872">
              <persName xml:lang="en">Marcus Fabius Quintilianus</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="horace" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/100227522">
              <persName xml:lang="en">Quintus Horatius Flaccus</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="varro" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/100219311">
              <persName xml:lang="en">Marcus Terentius Varro</persName>
            </person>
          </listPerson>
        </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div resp="#castelvetro">
        <head>
          <title xml:lang="it">Falli di parole</title>
          <title xml:lang="en">Word faults</title>
        </head>
        <div>
          <head>
            <title xml:lang="it">Mala elezione di parole forestiere</title>
            <title xml:lang="en">Poor choice of foreign words</title>
          </head>
          <div from="6r" to="9r" unit="folio">
            <div xml:lang="it">
              <p>
                <gap reason="editorial" />
                Poiché le parole latine sono straniere a’ vulgari, <gap reason="editorial" /> sì come non acconcie ad essere adoperate in questa canzone sono state da me segnate, e vanamente si producono dal <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> per sostegno loro l’autorità de’ valenti maestri di ritorica e di poesia, alcuni de’ quali non parlano di questa maniera di parole strane e alcuni ne parlano sì, ma niegano l’uso loro o non lo concedono in questo caso; sì come ancora s’adducono certi essempi di scrittori e alcune ragioni che non appertengono alla disputa nostra.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Il qual <persName ref="#quintilian">Quintiliano</persName>, dicendo che <persName ref="#horace">Orazio</persName> è <cit><q type="foreign" xml:lang="la">et varius figuris et verbis felicissime audax</q><bibl>Quintilian, Institutio Oratoria X 1,96</bibl></cit> <note type="translation" place="inline" resp="Antonino Maria Milazzo">variegato nelle forme del discorso e felicissimo innovatore nei vocaboli</note>, intende dell’arditezza di lui aventurosa solamente dentro da termini della lingua latina quanto appartiene alle voci; e dicendo

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                    nisi quod iniqui iudices adversus nos sumus, ideoque paupertate sermonis laboramus
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Quintilian, Institutio Oratoria VIII 3,33</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Franca Parodi Scotti">se non per il fatto che siamo troppo autocritici, ed è perciò che siamo afflitti dalla povertà del nostro lessico</note>

                intende egli della formazione delle parole latine a similitudine delle greche, e non del portare le forestiere <gap reason="editorial" /> in un’altra lingua, come mostra d’avere il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> per costante che intenda; e dicendo in due luoghi <q type="foreign" xml:lang="la">audendum</q> <note type="translation" place="inline" resp="#FM">bisogna osare</note> non intende universalmente delle voci d’ogni maniera di lingua forestiera, ma particolarmente delle voci formate di nuovo dal favellatore secondo la maniera della lingua <gap reason="editorial" /> straniera.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Ora, perché non sia una persona medesima secondo <persName ref="#varro">Varrone</persName> quella del favellatore e quella del poeta nell’usare l’analogia o la proporzione nelle parole; né perché non sia la ragione loro pari; né quella stessa potendo il poeta <cit><q type="foreign" xml:lang="la">transilire lineas impune</q><bibl>Varro, De Lingua Latina IX 5</bibl></cit>, cioè passare il segno, il che è interpretato da <persName ref="#varro">Varrone</persName> medesimo che il poeta può più liberamente seguire l’analogia nelle parole che non può il favellatore; non si concede miga per lui, secondo che presuppone il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>, che si conceda che il poeta possa mescolare voci strane <gap reason="editorial" /> nel suo poema, sì come altresì non si concede ciò per <persName ref="#horace">Orazio</persName> perché egli chiami l’uso generator delle parole, o perché dica che molte parole già morte rinasceranno, e molte, che sono in pregio, cadranno con questa condizione

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                    <lg>
                      <l>si volet usus</l>
                      <l>quem penes arbitrium est et ius et norma loquendi</l>
                    </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Horace, Ars Poetica 71–72</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Ugo Dotti">
                  <lg>
                    <l>se così vorrà l'uso,</l>
                    <l>che è il solo a essere legge, norma e diritto del nostro parlare</l>
                  </lg>
                </note>

                secondo che presupone il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> che si conceda. La podestà del quale uso è molto grande nel generar vocaboli e nel ravivare i già morti e nell’abbattere gli onorati, sì come dice <persName ref="#horace">Orazio</persName>, ma è picciola o nulla nel producere voci artificiose per significazione o per formazione, delle quali sole si parla in quelle parole oraziane

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                    <lg>
                      <l>Licuit semperque licebit</l>
                      <l>signatum præsente nota producere nomen</l>
                    </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Horace, Ars Poetica 58–59</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Ugo Dotti">
                  <lg>
                    <l>È sempre stato permesso (lo sarà pure domani)</l>
                    <l>imprimere nel nostro linguaggio il sigillo dell’oggi</l>
                  </lg>
                </note>

                pendendo del tutto questo lecito coniamento de’ vocaboli dall’ardire ingegnoso dello scrittore e non dalla forza del potente uso, come ingannandosi crede il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>
            </div>

            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
              <p>
                Since Latin words are foreign to vernacular speakers, <gap reason="editorial" /> I have marked them as not suited to be employed in this <foreign>canzone</foreign>, and in vain does <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> bring forth the authority of the eminent masters of rhetoric and poetry in their support, some of whom do not speak of this kind of foreign words, and some do speak of them, but deny their use or do not allow it in this case; just as he also adduces certain examples of writers and certain arguments that do not pertain to our dispute.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                As for <persName ref="#quintilian">Quintilian</persName>, in saying that <persName ref="#horace">Horace</persName> is <cit><q type="foreign" xml:lang="la">et varius figuris et verbis felicissime audax</q><bibl>Quintilian, Institutio Oratoria X 1,96</bibl></cit> <note type="translation" place="inline" resp="Donald A. Russell">versatile in his Figures, and felicitously daring in his choice of words</note> he means his daring as fortunate only within the bounds of the Latin language, as far as vocabulary is concerned; and in saying

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                    nisi quod iniqui iudices adversus nos sumus, ideoque paupertate sermonis laboramus
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Quintilian, Institutio Oratoria VIII 3,33</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Donald A. Russell">except that we are unreasonable critics of ourselves, and consequently suffer from poverty of language</note>

                he refers to the formation of Latin words after the model of Greek ones, and not to the importing of foreign words <gap reason="editorial" /> into another language, as <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> appears to assume; and in saying in two places <q type="foreign" xml:lang="la">audendum</q> <note type="translation" place="inline" resp="#FM">one must dare</note>, he does not mean it universally of words from every kind of foreign language, but specifically of words newly coined by the speaker following the manner of a foreign <gap reason="editorial" /> tongue.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Now, just because, according to <persName ref="#varro">Varro</persName>, the role of the speaker and that of the poet are not the same in the use of analogy or proportion in words; nor because they are governed by different principles; nor because the poet is allowed to <cit><q type="foreign" xml:lang="la">transilire lineas impune</q><bibl>Varro, De Lingua Latina IX 5</bibl></cit>, or pass the mark, which <persName ref="#varro">Varro</persName> himself interprets to mean that the poet may follow analogy in words more freely than the speaker can; it does not follow, as <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> assumes, that one should therefore grant the poet the license to mix foreign words <gap reason="editorial" /> into his poem, just as it does not follow in the case of <persName ref="#horace">Horace</persName> because he calls usage the begetter of words, or because he says that many words now dead will be reborn, and many that are esteemed will fall into this condition

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                    <lg>
                      <l>si volet usus</l>
                      <l>quem penes arbitrium est et ius et norma loquendi</l>
                    </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Horace, Ars Poetica 71–72</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Rushton Fairclough">
                  <lg>
                    <l>if Usage so will it,</l>
                    <l>in whose hands lies the judgement, the right and the rule of speech</l>
                  </lg>
                </note>

                as <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> presupposes that one should grant. The power of usage is indeed great in generating new words, in reviving the dead, and in bringing down those that are honored, as <persName ref="#horace">Horace</persName> says, but it is slight or null when it comes to producing artificial words either by signification or by formation, which are the ones under discussion in those Horatian lines

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                    <lg>
                      <l>Licuit semperque licebit</l>
                      <l>signatum præsente nota producere nomen</l>
                    </lg>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Horace, Ars Poetica 58–59</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Rushton Fairclough">
                  <lg>
                    <l>It has ever been, and ever will be,</l>
                    <l>permitted to issue words stamped with the mint-mark of the day</l>
                  </lg>
                </note>

                as all this liberty in coining words depends entirely on the ingenious daring of the writer, and not on the force of prevailing usage, which <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> mistakenly believes.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>
            </div>

            <note type="paraphrase">
            </note>

          </div>

          <div from="10v" to="11v" unit="folio">
            <div xml:lang="it">
              <p>
                Perché resta che veggiamo se, accostandoci noi all’opinione di messer <persName ref="#bembo">Pietro Bembo</persName>, che solo ha tenuto sermone di simiglianti voci, e all’essempio de’ poeti della lingua vulgare, le possiamo mantenere con lode nella canzone dove sono state poste dal <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>.
              </p>

              <p>
                Ma per apprender pienamente l’opinione di così riverendo scrittore intorno a ciò, e per sapere sicuramente dove e quando si permetta l’uso delle voci latine in canzone ad essempio de’ poeti vulgari, dico prima che sono da sciegliere certi scrittori d’autorità a quali si possa prestar fede nell’elezione delle parole; o più tosto sono da riconoscere i già scielti da messer <persName ref="#bembo">Pietro Bembo</persName>, e nominati da lui ne’ suoi libri della lingua vulgare, e citati a confermazione delle cose insegnateci, tra quali giudica essere il <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName> l’ottimo prosatore e ’l <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> l’ottimo rimatore, e amenduni gli ultimi in tempo da essere creduti.
              </p>

              <p>
                Ora il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> non si dovrebbe maravigliare se, dicendo egli che la lingua nostra è tenuta molto alla dottrina del <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName> nella scielta delle parole, io mi ritrarrò da dar molta credenza in questa parte a <persName ref="#lorenzo-medici">Lorenzo de’ Medici</persName>, o ad <persName ref="#poliziano">Angelo Poliziano</persName>, o ad alcun altro più moderno, poi che lo farò consigliato da esso <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName> approvato per buon consigliatore da esso <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                I volumi adunque riprovati da gli loro quantunque degni scrittori, o lasciatici imperfetti, o ripresi liberamente dal <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName> quanto è alla lingua, o trapassati per lui sotto taciturnità non ci possono rendere sicuri da biasimo se riempieremo i nostri scritti delle loro voci che non sieno altrove in volumi a quali non manchi né il fine, né il compiacimento del suo autore, né l’approvamento del <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName>.
              </p>

              <p>
                Ma non per tanto, oltre al predetto fine de’ volumi, e compiacimento de’ suoi autori, e approvamento del <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName>, è consiglio di <persName ref="#quintilian">Quintiliano</persName>, in questa materia d’usar le voci latine o altre ad essempio altrui, che si debba riguardare attentamente, ancora che non faccia errore chi usa le voci le quali hanno poste gli autori nobili ne’ suoi volumi, non tanto se que’ cotali abbiano poste quelle cotali voci, quanto se essi abbiano tirati de gli altri nel loro parere e avuti in ciò de’ seguaci.
              </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
              <p>
                What remains is to see whether, by coming close to the opinion of Messer <persName ref="#bembo">Pietro Bembo</persName>, who alone has discoursed on such words, and to the example of Italian poets, we may uphold them with merit in the <foreign>canzone</foreign> where they were placed by <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>.
              </p>

              <p>
                But in order to fully understand the opinion of so venerable a writer on this matter, and to know with certainty where and when the use of Latin words in a <foreign>canzone</foreign> is permitted after the example of Italian poets, I say first that one must select certain authoritative writers to trust regarding the choice of words; or rather, one should acknowledge those that Messer <persName ref="#bembo">Pietro Bembo</persName> has already selected, named in his books on the Italian language and cited in confirmation of the things he teaches us. Among them, he judges <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName> to be the finest prose writer, <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> the finest poet, and both the most recent in time to be worthy of consideration.
              </p>

              <p>
                Now <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> should not be surprised if, since he himself says that our language owes much to the doctrine of <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName> in the choice of words, I refrain from placing much trust in this regard in <persName ref="#lorenzo-medici">Lorenzo de’ Medici</persName>, in <persName ref="#poliziano">Angelo Poliziano</persName>, or in any other more recent author, since I do so on the advice of <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName> himself, whom <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> has approved as a sound counsellor.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Volumes, then, disavowed by their authors, however worthy, left to us incomplete, freely criticized by <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName> with regard to their language, or passed over by him in silence, cannot shield us from reproach if we fill our writings with their words, unless those words are also found in other volumes that lack neither final revision, nor the satisfaction of their author, nor the approval of <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName>.
              </p>

              <p>
                Nonetheless, beyond the aforementioned completeness of the volumes, the satisfaction of their authors, and the approval of <persName ref="#bembo">Bembo</persName>, it is the advice of <persName ref="#quintilian">Quintilian</persName>, in this matter of using Latin or other such words after the example of others, that one should carefully consider, so as not to err in using words which noble authors have placed in their volumes, not so much whether such authors happened to use those particular words, as whether they brought others to share their judgment and gained followers in this regard.   
              </p>
            </div>

            <note type="paraphrase">
            </note>

          </div>

          <div from="20v" to="21v" unit="folio">
            <div xml:lang="it">
              <p>
                Ma se il non avere usato il <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> queste voci <gap reason="editorial" /> si debba credere essere proceduto da giudicio, cioè perché egli non l’abbia giudicate degne delle sue scritture, o da altro accidente come da brevità di vita, o da strettezza, o da simplicità di materia, quasi dobbiamo pensare <gap reason="editorial" /> che, se più lungamente o d’altre materie avesse scritto, avrebbe usati altri modi di parlare e altre parole; e, sì come medesimamente afferma il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>, <gap reason="editorial" /> quasi possiamo dire che il <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> sia vissuto poco tempo, avendo egli menata la vita sua per lo spazio d’anni settanta interi meno un giorno per lo più sana, agiata e riposata, e non occupata in altro che ne gli studi graziosi di poesia; e abbia composti pochi sonetti e canzoni di soggetto non diverso, avendo egli scritto più lungamente, e più variamente in questa maniera di rime che facesse mai niuno altro che vivesse avanti a lui, o insieme con lui, o dopo lui. Ma, come io dico, se si debba stimare che ciò sia proceduto da giudiciosa deliberazione o da altro, non fa mestiere al presente che altro se ne dica.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Si può per le cose scritte in rime in tanta copia dal <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> in così lunga età, si può dico ottimamente discernere e sicuramente affermare quali parole fosse stato il <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> per usare e quali no, se fosse ancora vissuto più che non fece o avesse scritto più ampiamente o d’altra materia che non fece. Né chi dice di discerner ciò e l’afferma è tenuto al parer mio a produrre mandato fattogli dal <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> della sua volontà e di quello che fosse stato egli in ciò per fare o per non fare, non si potendo aver maggior certezza della volontà altrui non palesata e di quello che egli volesse fare o non fare da altro che dal tenore dell’altre simili azioni servate per l’adietro da lui. Né parimente è tenuto a confessare che lo spirito del <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> o l’anima sia passata nel suo corpo secondo la palingenesia Pitagorica o Cabalistica, o a vantarsi d’avere avuto ciò per divina spirazione o rivelazione, secondo che il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> dice, prendendo in giuoco quelle mie parole <q corresp="#parere-1-it">il Petrarca non userebbe</q>, che io sono tenuto a fare poi che affermo di discernerlo. Ma senza producimento di mandato, o confessione di passamento di spirito o d’anima in nuovo corpo, o vanto di spirazione divina o di rivelazione, il <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> mi potrà pur credere, poi che io sono secondo le sue parole molto pratico nel vocabolario, che egli, il quale non v’è così pratico, s’inganna a negare che nel <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> sieno le voci <mentioned>famelico</mentioned>, <mentioned>eternare</mentioned>, <mentioned>lentare</mentioned>, percioché nel vocabolario della memoria mia è registrato <mentioned>famelico</mentioned> come detto dal <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> in quel verso <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
              <p>
                But whether <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName>'s not having used these words <gap reason="editorial" /> should be believed to have proceeded from judgment—that is, because he did not deem them worthy of his writings—or from some other circumstance, such as the brevity of his life, or the narrowness or simplicity of his subject matter, as though we ought to think <gap reason="editorial" /> that, had he written longer or on other subjects, he would have used other modes of expression and other words; and, just as <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> likewise affirms, <gap reason="editorial" /> we may almost say that <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> lived a short life, though he passed seventy full years less one day for the most part in good health, comfort, and repose, and occupied with nothing other than the pleasing studies of poetry; and composed few sonnets and <foreign>canzoni</foreign> on no diverse subject, although he wrote more extensively and with greater variety in this form of verse than did any other who lived before him, or with him, or after him. But, as I say, whether this is to be considered the result of deliberate judgment or of some other cause, it is not necessary at present to say more of it.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                From the works written in rhyme by <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> in such quantity and over so long a life, it may, I say, most clearly be discerned and safely affirmed which words <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> would have used and which he would not, had he lived longer than he did, or had he written more extensively or on other subjects than he did. Nor is he who claims to discern this, in my opinion, bound to produce a warrant granted by <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> declaring his will and what he would or would not have done in this matter, for greater certainty of another’s unexpressed will, and of what he intended to do or not to do, cannot be had than from the tenor of his other like actions previously preserved by him. Nor, likewise, is he bound to confess that the spirit or soul of <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> passed into his body according to Pythagorean or Kabbalistic metempsychosis, or to boast of having had such knowledge by divine inspiration or revelation, as <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> says, jesting at my words <q corresp="#parere-1-en">Petrarch would not use</q>, that I am bound to do, since I claim to discern it. But without producing any warrant, or confessing the passage of soul or spirit into a new body, or boasting of divine inspiration or revelation, <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> may yet believe me, since, according to his own words, I am well-versed in the vocabulary; and he, who is not so well-versed in it, is mistaken in denying that in <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> are to be found the words <mentioned><foreign>famelico</foreign></mentioned>, <mentioned><foreign>eternare</foreign></mentioned>, <mentioned><foreign>lentare</foreign></mentioned>, because in the vocabulary of my memory <mentioned><foreign>famelico</foreign></mentioned> is recorded as said by <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> in the verse <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>
            </div>

            <note type="paraphrase">
            </note>

          </div>

          <div from="23r" to="24r" unit="folio">
            <div xml:lang="it">
              <p>
                Se adunque non segnai le parole latine nella canzone del <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName> perché solamente il <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> non l’avesse usate, ma per altro, come evidentemente appare per quello che è stato detto, e appareva ancora, fuori di raggione m’appone egli che io voglia ristringere tutta la favella volgare dentro da termini del <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> e del <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName>; e fuori di tempo mi ridice tre volte, per un grandissimo e bellissimo secreto, e non udito prima da un par mio, che la lingua che si parla e per conseguente vive ancora, quale è la vulgare nostra, non si prende in formare i nostri scritti tutta da molti libri e tanto meno da un solo, come si fanno quelle che più non si parlano e sono morte, se non in quanto vivono ne libri degli scrittori, quali sono la latina e la greca; ma, in buona parte, si prende ancora da molti che la parlano, quasi che le voci latine da me segnate si parlino. Ora, non s’avede egli dicendo ciò, o fa vista di non avedersi, di contradire a messer <persName ref="#bembo">Pietro Bembo</persName>, il quale ci consiglia a scrivere non con vocaboli del popolo o del tempo presente, in tutto o in parte, ma con que’ degli autori antichi e dalla loro età, nella lingua vulgare e in ogni altra lingua, quando i vocaboli degli autori e dell’età passata sono migliori che non sono que’ del popolo o dell’età nostra; sì come sono migliori gli usati, secondo ch’egli afferma, dal <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName> e da <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> e dal suo secolo, che non sono quelli che usiamo oggidì noi.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Senza che, fuori di ragione, si maraviglia del mio giudicio, apponendomi falsamente che io pensi che di necessità si debba prendere tutta la favella con la quale scriviamo dagli scritti d’un solo, contra lo ’nsegnamento di <persName ref="#quintilian">Quintiliano</persName>

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                     Sed non qui maxime imitandus, et solus imitandus est
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Quintilian, Institutio Oratoria X 2,24</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Antonino Maria Milazzo">Ma l’autore che deve essere imitato di preferenza non deve essere anche l’unico a essere imitato</note>

                apponendo a lui, o per ignoranza o per malizia, che intenda in quel motto della rassomiglianza delle parole, il quale non dimeno intende della rassomiglianza delle altre virtù del favellatore, come vedrà manifestamente chi guarderà ben quel luogo. Ma, senza apporre a lui quel che non pensa, mi posso ben maravigliar di lui, che, per accattarmi odio appresso le persone, ancora per questa via dica che altro non è il proporre il <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName> e ’l <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarca</persName> per essempio unico delle scritture, presuponendo egli che io gli proponga quanto è alla favella, che un ristringere la religione Cristiana tutta nel testamento nuovo, senza voler ricevere le tradizioni de’ padri; le quali, secondo che egli dice, deono aver luogo non meno nella lingua vulgare che nel Cristianesimo, non riconoscendo egli la gran dissimilitudine che è tra le tradizioni de’ padri santi Cristiani e le tradizioni de’ suoi pari, che egli intende di proporci per padri in questa lingua. Percioché, dove quelle scoprono la gloria dell’evangelio, e ristringono la licenza del dissoluto viver mondano, e mortificano la carne per vivificar lo spirito, queste oscurano la chiarezza della lingua, e rallargano ogni strettezza d’osservato parlare, e essaltano e diffendono la ignoranza per abbassare e confondere la scienza.
              </p>
            </div>
            
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="en">
              <p>
                If, then, I did not mark the Latin words in <persName ref="#caro">Caro</persName>’s canzone merely because <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> had not used them, but for other reasons, as clearly appears from what has been said, and was evident even before, it is unjust of him to accuse me of wishing to confine the entire vernacular Italian within the limits set by <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> and <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName>. And it is belated of him to repeat to me three times, as if it were some great and beautiful secret, unheard of by one of my station, that a living language such as our vernacular, which is still spoken and thus still alive, is not formed for our writing entirely from books, and much less from a single book, as happens with those languages no longer spoken and now dead, except insofar as they live in the books of their authors, such as Latin and Greek. Rather, it is formed in large part also from the usage of many who speak it, as though the Latin words I marked were currently spoken. Now, in saying this, does he not perceive, or does he pretend not to perceive, that he is contradicting Messer <persName ref="#bembo">Pietro Bembo</persName>, who advises us to write not with the words of the people or of the present age, in whole or in part, but with those of the ancient authors and of their time, in Italian as in any other language, whenever the words of past authors and of past times are better than those of the people or of our present age? Such, according to him, are the words used by <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName> and <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> and by their century, which he holds to be superior to those that we use today.
                <gap reason="editorial" />
              </p>

              <p>
                Moreover, it is unjust that he should be surprised by my judgment, falsely accusing me of thinking that one must necessarily draw the entire language in which we write from the writings of a single author, against the teaching of <persName ref="#quintilian">Quintilian</persName>:

                <cit>
                  <quote type="foreign" xml:lang="la">
                     Sed non qui maxime imitandus, et solus imitandus est
                  </quote>
                  <bibl>Quintilian, Institutio Oratoria X 2,24</bibl>
                </cit>
                <note type="translation" place="below" resp="Donald A. Russell">The author who is most to be imitated is not also the only author to be imitated</note>

                falsely attributing to him—whether out of ignorance or of malice—the intention to speak in that remark of the likeness of words, whereas in fact he speaks of the likeness of the other virtues of the speaker, as one will clearly see if they look carefully at that passage. But without attributing to him what he does not believe, I may well be surprised at him, who, in order to turn others against me, also goes so far as to say that proposing <persName ref="#boccaccio">Boccaccio</persName> and <persName ref="#petrarca">Petrarch</persName> as the sole model for writing—supposing that I do indeed propose them as such with regard to language—is nothing else than reducing the whole of the Christian religion to the New Testament, refusing to accept the traditions of the Fathers. These, he says, ought to have a place no less in vernacular Italian than in Christianity, failing to recognize the great difference between the traditions of the holy Christian Fathers and the traditions of his peers, whom he intends to propose to us as Fathers in this language. For whereas the former reveal the glory of the Gospel, restrain the license of dissolute worldly living, and mortify the flesh to give life to the spirit, the latter obscure the clarity of the language, loosen all discipline of measured speech, and exalt and defend ignorance in order to cast down and confound knowledge.
              </p>
            </div>

            <note type="paraphrase">
            </note>

          </div>

        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>